Choosing a Mate
I am a single, working woman.
I want a family and to be
a good mother and wife
while I practice Jungto's goal of
pursuing purity and freedom.
But, I am not sure
who could help me to achieve it.
I think someone I can respect
would be good,
but, when I am actually with him,
I feel uneasy and distant.
The one I am comfortable with,
as people say, is inferior to me.
I am easy with him
because I want to feel superior.
But, I can't ignore
how the society would view him.
I am having a hard time
because I want to be subservient.
I know men have strong pride.
He may like me now.
And he is blind to the fact
that I act superior.
But, as time goes by, he may get hurt and
distance himself from me.
I know "You reap what you sow."
But, I forget it often.
I would like to hear from you
how I should practice.
First of all, your desire of purity
and freedom cannot coexist
with your being good mother and wife.
You are trying to accomplish
two that are incompatible.
It's the same thing as I want to be a
good monk and marry and have children.
They cannot coexist.
You have to give up one.
If you want to be 'free', as you say,
give up marriage and join Jungto
and become a practitioner.
Or, work and have a
small place of your own
and do as you please.
You need the mindset of a servant
to be a good mother and wife.
You need the mindset to be your
husband's servant, to follow his will.
If you go into your marriage
foolishly thinking you can be both,
you will soon find out
that it doesn't work.
You will be unhappy and run away.
Later, if you marry someone
who is smarter than you,
you can't lower yourself even you want.
And someone who likes you
will turn out to be inferior to you.
That is the truth.
There will be pain
no matter whom you choose.
Because if you choose someone
who is superior to you,
he won't be satisfied with a woman
who is inferior to him.
He will be looking at other women.
He will look elsewhere.
And you will be in pain with jealousy.
Someone likes you now
because your are better than him.
You look perfect to him now.
Why?
Because he is inferior to you.
He even likes your arrogance
with your nose stuck in the air.
He even likes you throwing a fit.
But, once you get married,
you think he would listen to you
and be your servant.
But, once you get married, he won't.
And you have to support him all your life.
You have to support him and
you have to take care of everything.
Every time you say something,
he will think
you are looking down on him and get upset.
It will be a huge headache.
(Audience Laughter)
So, either way, you will have a problem.
Why does this happen?
Because your thought is wrong
to start with.
It's not important
whether he is smarter than you or not.
A superior man, a smart man, is good
for a realistic gain.
An inferior man is good
because he would be nice and docile.
A docile man is incompetent.
A competent man won't be as nice.
He is mean and
you have to be subservient,
but, you would rather die
than be subservient.
You don't want to hear
to marry an incompetent man
You don't want to hear that
people saying you married wrong.
All this is greed.
Stop thinking like that.
Marriage is
where two different people meet
and live together with respect,
respecting each other as they are.
That's what I say
when I am talking to a couple together.
When I talk to only one of them,
I say, be agreeable and obedient
to the other no matter what.
You need this kind of determination.
Because there will be conflicts if you
try to change the other to fit your needs.
You can get married
when you are ready to be obedient.
You should start practicing.
You can say "Yes, I will"
in any case,
"What's the worst that could happen?
The worst thing would be death."
And you must let it go.
You over-think trying to figure out
who would be better.
This one has a nice personality.
That one is rich.
That one is educated.
That one is handsome.
You may think all night.
But, in the morning,
you will be even more confused.
So, stop that right now.
Did you say you went to
the Enlightenment Retreat?
OK. Stop all your thinking
and pray for 100 days.
(Questioner) I am in the middle
of 1000-Day Practice.
(Questioner) I feel I am not centered
because I don't have a prayer mantra.
You are greedy,
not that you are not centered.
Pray, "I lack in many ways."
"I lack in many ways."
"I will practice with great devotion
for enlightenment."
"Whoever marries me
will be a great person."
"I will serve him."
Pray like that.
It's not good when someone pursues you
because he likes you.
You are a master
when you like him and pursue him.
But the person you love
seems like the master, right?
What do you think?
When you love him, but he doesn't love
you, he seems to be the master, right?
But you are the master.
Why?
Who has control over loving him
or not loving him?
Yourself.
When a guy keeps pursuing you,
you feel like you are the master, right?
It seems like you are the master
and he is your servant.
But, you can't control
his feelings or behaviors.
You have to look closely.
(Questioner) I will follow my heart,
keeping in mind what you have said.
(Questioner) But my parents are
actually against him...
If you really love him, it should not
matter if your parents are against him.
So what if you end up penniless
as long as you love him?
You know the story of a princess
marrying a pauper.
You support him to become great man
after you marry him. That's love.
It is not love to seek benefit
from a marriage.
(Questioner) Thank you.